<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The effect of certaine branches of the statute made in anno 33 Henrici viij touching the maintenance of artillery, and the punishment of such as vse vnlawfull games, very necessary to be put in execution</title>
            <title>Laws, etc.</title>
            <author>England and Wales.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1632</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 5 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A22555</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 8994.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S3173</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">33143103</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 33143103</idno>
            <idno type="VID">28232</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A22555)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 28232)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1876:142)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The effect of certaine branches of the statute made in anno 33 Henrici viij touching the maintenance of artillery, and the punishment of such as vse vnlawfull games, very necessary to be put in execution</title>
                  <title>Laws, etc.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.).   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Robert Barker, Printer to the Kings most Excellent Maiestie: And by the Assignes of Iohn Bill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.DC.XXXII [1632]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Extract from original text of statute.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Society of Antiquaries.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bow and arrow --  Law and legislation --  Great Britain.</term>
               <term>Games --  Law and legislation --  Great Britain.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles I, 1625-1649.</term>
               <term>Broadsides --  London (England) --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="document">
            <pb facs="tcp:28232:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 7 -->
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <head>C R</head>
                  <q>DIEV ET MON DROIT</q>
                  <q>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
                  <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <head>¶ The effect of certaine branches of the Statute made in Anno 33. Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rici viij. touching the maintenance of Artillery, and the puniſhment of ſuch as vſe vnlawfull games, very neceſſary to be put in execution.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>FIrſt, that all Fathers, Gouernours, and rulers of ſuch as be tender of age, doe teach and</hi> bring them vp in the knowledge of Shooting, and that euery man hauing a man child, or men children in his houſe, ſhall prouide, ordaine, and haue in his houſe for euery man child, beeing of the age of ſeuen yeeres and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue, till he ſhall come to the age of ſeuenteene yeeres, a Bowe and two Shafts, to induce and learne them, and bring them vp in Shooting, and ſhall deliuer all the ſame Bow and Arrowes to the ſame yong men to vſe and occupy. And if the ſame yong men be ſeruants, that then their maſter ſhal abate the money that they ſhall pay for the ſame Bowes and Arrowes of their wages. And after all ſuch yong men ſhall come to the age of ſeuenteene yeeres, euery of them ſhall prouide and haue a Bowe &amp; foure Arrowes continually for himſelfe, at his proper coſt and charges, or elſe of the gift or prouiſion of his friends, and vſe and occupie the ſame in Shooting, as is before rehearſed. And if the maſter ſuffer any of his ſeruants taking wages, being in his houſhold, and vnder the age of ſeuenteen yeeres, to lacke a Bow and two Arrowes, contrary to the forme of this Eſtatute, by the ſpace of one moneth together, then the maſter or fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in whom ſuch negligence ſhall bee, ſhall for euery ſuch default forfeit vi. s. viii. d. And that euery ſeruant, paſſing the age of ſeuenteene yeeres, and vnder the age of threeſcore yeeres, and taking wages, which can, or is able to ſhoot, and ſhall lacke a Bow and foure Arrowes by the ſpace of one moneth together, ſhall for euery ſuch default forfeit and loſe vi. s. vii. d.</p>
            <p>ITem, that no perſon by himſelfe, Factor, Deputy, ſeruant, or other perſon, ſhall for his or their gaine, lucre, or li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, keepe, haue, hold, occupy, exerciſe or maintaine any common houſe, alley, or place of Bowling, Coiting, Cloiſe, Coiles, halfe bowle, Tennis, Dicing, Table, or Carding, or any other manner of Game, prohibited by any Statute heretofore made, or any vnlawfull new game now inuented or made, or hereafter to be inuented, found, had or made, vpon paine to forfeit and pay for euery day, keeping, hauing, maintaining, or ſuffering any ſuch game to be had, kept, executed, played, or maintained within any ſuch Houſe, Garden, Alley, or other place, contrary to the forme and effect of this Eſtatute xl. s. and the players ſo taken, to pay for euery time vi. s. viii. d.</p>
            <p>ITem, That the Iuſtices of Peace, and euery Maior, Sheriffe, Bailiffe, Conſtable, or other head officer, haue au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to enter into all places, aſwell within Franchiſes or elſewhere, and the perſons offending in any of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſes, to take and put in priſon, vntill ſuch time they put in Sureties no more to ſuffer, occupy, or commit the ſayd offences.</p>
            <p>ITem, that all Maiors, Sheriffes, Bayliffes, Conſtables, and other head Officers within euery Citie, Borough, and Towne within this Realme, where any ſuch Officers ſhall fortune to bee, aſwell within the Franchiſes as without, ſhall make due ſearch weekely, or at the furtheſt at all times hereafter once euery Moneth in all places, where any ſuch Houſe, Alleys, Play, or Players ſhall be ſuſpected to be had, kept, and maintained. And if the ſayd Maiors, Sheriffes, Bayliffes, Conſtables, and other head Officers within their Cities, Boroughs, and Townes, aſwell within Franchiſes as without, doe not make due ſearch at the furtheſt once euery moneth, if the caſe ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, according to the tenor of this Act, and doe not execute the ſame in all things, according to the purport and force of the ſame: that then euery ſuch Maior, Sheriffes, Bayliffes, Conſtables, or other head Officer, to pay and forfeit for euery moneth not making ſuch ſearch, nor executing the ſame. xl. s.</p>
            <p>ITem, That no Artificer, or Handicrafts man of any occupation, Huſbandman, Apprentice, Labourer, ſeruant of Huſbandry, Iourneyman, or ſeruant, or Artificer, Mariner, Fiſherman, Waterman, or any Seruingman, may vſe any vnlawfull Game.</p>
            <p>ITem, That all play at Bowles, or any other vnlawfull Game in the fields, to loſe for euery ſuch time vi. s. viii. d. and to be committed to priſon, vnto ſuch time they put in Sureties no more to vſe the ſame.</p>
            <p>ITem, This Statute to bee proclaimed foure times euery yeere, and the like to bee done in all Aſſiſes and Seſſions, and to continue for euer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>MEmorandum,</hi> That there is a Prouiſo in this Statute, for all men of worſhip, which may diſpend one hundred pounds yeerely and vpwards, may vſe theſe Games with diſcretion at their pleaſures.</p>
            <closer>God ſaue the King.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Imprinted at London by ROBERT BARKER, Printer to the Kings moſt Excellent MAIESTIE: And by the Aſsignes of IOHN BILL. M.DC.XXXII.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
